<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short exposition of the 20. and 21. verses of the third chapter of the first epistle of S. Iohn Containing a very profitable discourse of conscience, and of al the actions, sortes, and kinds thereof, wherby euery man may easily know his estate, wherein hee standeth in the sight of his God, and whether his conscience be good or euill, with all things also belonging either to get a good conscience, or else to releiue it out of trouble, being grieued and wounded, as in the epistle to the reader is more specially mentioned, and in the discourse itselfe clearely expressed.</title>
            <author>Howesoun, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03759</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13878</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116556</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851772</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851772</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17063</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03759)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17063)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 711:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short exposition of the 20. and 21. verses of the third chapter of the first epistle of S. Iohn Containing a very profitable discourse of conscience, and of al the actions, sortes, and kinds thereof, wherby euery man may easily know his estate, wherein hee standeth in the sight of his God, and whether his conscience be good or euill, with all things also belonging either to get a good conscience, or else to releiue it out of trouble, being grieued and wounded, as in the epistle to the reader is more specially mentioned, and in the discourse itselfe clearely expressed.</title>
                  <author>Howesoun, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Waldegraue, printer to the Kings Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1600.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: M. Iohn Howesoun.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A discourse of conscience.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Foot of title page has: Cum priuilegio Regio.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conscience --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17063:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17063:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17063:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17063:2"/>
            <p>A <hi>SHORT EXPOSITI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the</hi> 20. <hi>and</hi> 21. <hi>verſes</hi> of the third Chapter of the firſt <hi>Epiſtle of S. Iohn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>CONTAINING A VERY PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable diſcourſe of conſcience, and of al the actions, ſortes, and kinds thereof, wherby euery man may eaſily know his eſtate, wherein hee ſtandeth in the ſight of his God, and whether his conſcience be good or euill, with all things alſo belonging either to get a good conſcience, or elſe to releiue it out of trouble, being grieued and woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as in the epiſtle to the reader is more ſpecially mentioned, and in the diſcourſe itſelfe clearely expreſſed.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 15. verſe 15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>A good conſcience is a continuall feaſt</p>
            </q>
            <p>EDINBVRGH. PRINTED BY ROBERT <hi>WAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>degraue, Printer to the Kings Maieſtie.</hi> Anno Dom. 1600.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum privilegio Regio.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:17063:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17063:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lbeit the dulneſſe of this time be ſuch, (gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Reader in the Lord) that it rather mooueth manie to content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with other mens writings, then to take paines, to write for the profite of any thing themſelues: yet ſuch is the zeale of ſome, that they cannot ſuffer men to ſleep in the danger of ſinne to their owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, but wil (if it be posſible) awake them, &amp; let them know the deadly dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger wherein they ſtand, which is a thing moſt needful, although it be neyther plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to the worlde nor acceptable to the fleſh: for who is he that ſeeth not the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the world in this age, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of God and of his word, and doth not ſorrow at the heart for it. And ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is not posſible, that any can truely ſorrow, and ſit ſtill and ſay nothing, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, when he perceaueth the moſte part of all this blind age, by the craft of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, caſt into a deadly ſleepe of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſecurity. So that they neither care for the true knowledge of God, while they
<pb facs="tcp:17063:4"/>
are young; nor think that they ſtand in neede of it being olde, but ſpend, or rather miſpend all their time in the vain cares and pleaſures of this tranſitorie world, without heedfull care vnto their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, or giuing eare vnto their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence when the ſame accuſeth them, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victeth them, and condemneth them before God, as guiltie of infinite thinges, whereof one day they muſt giue an exact accounte, and at his handes receaue the wages of eternall death for their works, vnleſſe they awake, while time is, truelie repent them of their former ſecurity, &amp; trye al their actions, thoughts, words &amp; deedes, by euery mans conſcience, the which the Lord hath giuen him, both to be vnto him witneſſe and iudge of the ſame. And therfore, to the ende that al men may doe this the better, to whoſe hearing or reading this diſcourſe ſhall come. I haue thought it good, being moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in my conſcience, to write this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe therof. Wherby eueryman may know his owne eſtate and his God, as he hath
<pb facs="tcp:17063:4"/>
revealed himſelfe in his worde to the worlde. Both the which points (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) are aboue all things neceſſary for all men that deſire to eſcape hell, and come to heauen. For as of the knowledge of thy ſelfe, commeth the feare of God &amp; of the knowledge of God, the loue of God; ſo of the ignorance of thy ſelfe, commeth pride, and of the ignorance of God &amp; of his word, deſperation (ſaith he). Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, whoſoeuer will avoyde this deadlie dart of deſperation in the ende, muſt not neglect the meanes which God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted to eſcape it. That is, firſt to know his ſins, and heare his conſcience, vvhen ſhe accuſeth or excuſeth him according to the rule of Gods word. And next, to know the way of deliuerance from them And that he take heed, that in ſeeking a ſalue for them, he be not deceaued therin for conſcience being wounded with ſin, is that thing that neither can bee healed with coulors of Retorick, with ſweetnes of muſick, with delicacie of daintie meates, with beawtie and pleaſant ſights, with
<pb facs="tcp:17063:5"/>
mans inuentions, or elſe with any other thing except onely Chriſt, as he hath offe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red and revealed himſelfe in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, apprehended by faith, &amp; receaued and kept with a good conſcience, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the which, if any man liue &amp; dye, it had bin farre better for him, that vvith <hi>Kain</hi> &amp; <hi>Iudas</hi> he had neuer bin borne. Receaue therefore (gentle reader) this ſhort diſcourſe, wherein thou mayeſt ſee both what a thing conſcience is, what an intollerable thing the grief &amp; wound thereof is when it is troubled. What are all the actions, and offices of it in al men and women. What are the ſorts &amp; kinds thereof: what is mans duety touching it. How to get a good conſcience, &amp; keepe it being gotten: and laſtly, how to relieue &amp; helpe it being troubled, that it accuſe and condemne vs not before our God, whoſe ſentence when it accuſeth, ſhall euer ſtand &amp; condemne vs without reclamation be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the Lord. But if not, then ſhall vve haue boldnes towards our God, to whom be glory for euer.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:17063:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. IOHN CHAP. 3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="20">
                     <hi>20</hi> If our heart condemne vs, God is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then our heart, and knoweth all things.</p>
                  <p n="21">
                     <hi>21</hi> Beloued, if our heart condemne vs not, then haue we boldnes toward God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Apoſtle in theſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> words doth teach vs that ſeeing the knowledge of God doth infinit degrees paſſe the vnderſtanding of our harts or conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. It muſt needs therfore follow, that none can ſtand before his holie maieſty, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the integritie of a pure and good conſcience. In the teſtimonie whereof, conſiſteth all our comfort and reioycing ſaith <hi>Paul.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2, Cor. 1.12.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In this place <hi>Iohn</hi> doth neither ſpeak <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> of the conſcience of reprobates,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.19. Math. 9.12.</note> who are paſt feeling, and giuen themſelues to worke vncleanes euen with greedines. Neither yet of Hypocrites, who flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring themſelues, doe boaſt them of their
<pb facs="tcp:17063:6"/>
owne righteouſnes. But onely of them that haue their conſcience drawen forth before the iudgement ſeate of God, by him to make them vnderſtand and feele his anger and wrath againſt them,<note place="margin">Pſal. 6.3. &amp; 38.3. &amp;. 51 4. 1. Sam. 2 6</note> In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of ſome ſinnes, whereof their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience dooth accuſe them, that they ſhould ſpeedely turne vnto him, that he may heale them whoe hath wounded them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> In the 21 verſe, hee ſheweth by the contrarie, how greate a treaſure it is to men or wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to haue euer the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of a good conſcience, for then (ſaith he) if the ſame accuſe vs not, as guiltie of anie offence vnto our God, whereof we doe not from our heart repent vs, with aſſurance of pardon for Chriſt his ſake, in whome we onely beleeue to finde all that we ſtand in neede of. Then may we without feare, both approch with bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and come before the throne &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſeate of our God, call him our louing father,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.1, Ephe. 3.12</note> and aſſure our ſelues that he will be fauorable and mercifull vnto vs for his Chriſts ſake, by whom we haue both boldnes and enterance with confidence by faith, through whome alſo we haue
<pb facs="tcp:17063:6"/>
that peace with him (ſayth the Apoſtle) in our Conſcience, that paſſeth all Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, yea all vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>Not that anie mans conſcience bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> him witnes that he is without ſinne:<note place="margin">Pſal. 130.3. &amp;. 143. 2 Ezch. 18, 21 Zach, 1.3. Math 11.28.</note> But becauſe hee dooth acknowledge his ſins, confeſſeth them to his God, repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth him therof, beleeueth in Chriſt, and ſubmitteth himſelfe and his will whollie to the will of his God, deſiring aboue all things, euer to be ruled and gouerned thereby onely.</p>
            <p>Of all this, I marke only here,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Tim, 48 The frute both of godlines &amp; of ſinne what</note> what is the gaine of godlines, that is, of faith, &amp; of a good conſcience, even a promiſe to haue al things neceſſarie for this life, and likewiſe to enioy life everlaſting, made by God himſelfe in the ſcriptures, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in alſo, and in this place eſpecially, we finde the crueltie of ſinne to bee ſo huge &amp; weighty, that by no meanes that man can finde in himſelfe, he ſhal euer be able to ſhake of the intollerabl burthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof, that thereby at one time or another, his conſcience ſhall not be fearefully wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened, greeued, and aboue all thinges burthened therewith, and not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that the wages thereof, is death e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting,
<pb facs="tcp:17063:7"/>
both of bodie and ſoule. And therefore, they are farre deceaued, who flattering themſelues in their ſinnes, goe about to ſhift themſelues from the ſenſe and feeling of Gods wrath, and the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of their own conſcience, to accuſe convict, and to condemne them before his tribunall ſeate for the ſame: of which ſort, notwithſtanding there hath bin in all ages an infinite number, who as the Prophet ſayth: <hi>Hath made a couenant with deathe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 28.15.</note> 
               <hi>and are at agreement with Hell.</hi> That albeit a ſcourge come, it ſhall not touch them, and that by reaſon of their ſhifts, their refuges, &amp; their cloaks of falſhood and vanitie, wherewith they ſuppoſe to couer their ſinne from God. But all in vaine (ſaith the Lorde) for the ſcourge of wrath ſhal come, tredde them downe, and vtterlie conſume them. And yet of this kind of people (ſaith the Lord) the world ſhal be ful in the latter daies,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.3.6.</note> who when they ſhall looke for nothing but peace and ſafetie, then ſhall come vp on them vndoubtedly death and endles deſtruction, the which ſhould learne vs not any longer to ſleepe in ſinne, and to contemne wholeſome admonitions, as
<pb facs="tcp:17063:7"/>
doth the moſte part of all the worlde at this day, to their own loſſe and perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all deſtruction,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.16.</note> but haiſtilie and with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence to awake (as ſaith the Apoſtle) who hytherto haue without remorſe of conſcience and true repentance, ſlept in ſinne, and filthie luſtes of our fleſh. The which at length, bringeth forth death both of bodie and ſoule, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, he commandeth vs to ryſe from the ſame by faith, repentance, and newnes of life. That by Chriſt we may receaue the light of life euerlaſting and the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of our conſciences,<note place="margin">Heb. 9.4. The deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this diſcourſe is foure-folde.</note> from dead works to ſerue the liuing God. The which as they are, eyther good or bad in all men and women. So am I minded, firſt to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe and ſet downe the true definition of conſcience. The which heare the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle calleth the <hi>Heart</hi> of man, &amp; what a greefe it is to haue the ſame hurte, and wounded with ſinne. Secondly, to ſhew what are the proper dueties and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thereof in all perſons. Thirdly, what are the kindes and diuerſitie of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences. And laſt, what bee the dueties of al men and women touching their owne conſciences: how to preuent the troubles
<pb facs="tcp:17063:8"/>
therof, and alſo how to releeue the ſame being troubled.</p>
            <p>Concerning the firſt, I finde this word <hi>hearte</hi> in the Scriptures,<note place="margin">1 The heart of man what.</note> to haue diuerſe ſignifications, &amp; therefore placed ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for the affections of the <hi>hearte,</hi> as <hi>Where your treaſure is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6.21.</note> 
               <hi>there vvill your hearte be alſo.</hi> Some times for the whole ſoule of man: as, <hi>Let the hid man of the heart be vncorrupt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3, 4,</note> Some times for the will of man:<note place="margin">Act. 4, 31,</note> as, <hi>they were all of one heart,</hi> that is, they were all of one minde, will or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: and ſometimes for mans conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: as in that prayer which <hi>Paull</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth for the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 3.</note> praying, <hi>that the Lorde ſhoulde make their heartes ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and vnblameable, in holineſſe before God, at the comming of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi> That is, their conſcience, as now in the words and text aboue ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. The Apoſtle Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth by the word <hi>Heart,</hi> the onely conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of man.</p>
            <p>For as hee conſiſteth of two partes principallie,<note place="margin">2 The diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the parts of man in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy &amp; ſoule.</note> that is, of bodie &amp; ſoule. So doth the ſoule conſiſt of <hi>vnderſtanding</hi> and <hi>will,</hi> albeit the ſoule hath no partes properly, but onely by analogie, and in
<pb facs="tcp:17063:8"/>
reſpect of the diuerſe obiects and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thereof: By reaſon whereof, the ſame is ſaid to bee deuided into diuers parts, that is, into diuers powers or faculties.</p>
            <p>The <hi>vnderſtanding,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3 vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding what</note> is called that power or facultie of the ſoule, whereby we vſe reaſon, which is the more princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall part, ſeruing to rule and to order the whole man. And therefore it is placed in the ſoule, to guyde and gouerne the whole perſon.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Wil,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4 Will what</note> is that facultie and power of the ſoule, whereby we do will or nill anie thing. That is, chuſe or refuſe it.</p>
            <p>With the <hi>Wil</hi> are ioyned certaine af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, as <hi>Ioy, Sorrow, Loue, Hatred,</hi>
               <note place="margin">5 Affections are ioyned with the will.</note> and ſick-like, whereby wee doe eyther im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace or eſchew that which is good or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill.</p>
            <p>Now,<note place="margin">6 Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience not placed i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the ſoule,</note> becauſe the workes and actions of conſcience doe ſtand in the vſe of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, it is euident, that therefore it is not placed in the affections or willing parte of the ſoule, but in the vnderſtanding, which hath alſo two parts.</p>
            <p>The firſt whereof is,<note place="margin">7 Two parts of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</note> that which ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in the view and contemplation of the trueth or falſhood of any thinge, and
<pb facs="tcp:17063:9"/>
goeth no further.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theoricall</hi> and <hi>Practicall</hi> wherein conſcience is placed.</note> The ſecond, is that which ſtandeth in the view of euery par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular action, to ſearch and ſeeke whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſame bee good or euill. The firſte is called <hi>Theoricall,</hi> and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde <hi>Practical.</hi> Vnder the which conſcience is comprehended: becauſe her propertie is to iudge of the goodnes or badnes of things or turnes done.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">8 The defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of Conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce <hi>Tho. aqui part,</hi> 1. <hi>que</hi> 79. <hi>artic.</hi> 13</note>So that of theſe premiſſes we haue to vnderſtand, that conſcience is a parte of the minde or vnderſtanding in all reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable creatures: determining, iudgeing, decerning, and giuing ſentence of all their particular actions, thoughts, words or deedes, eyther with them or againſt them.</p>
            <p>This definiſion of conſcience doth ſhew,<note place="margin">9 Conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is not a bare know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge with out works of accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing, &amp;c</note> that it is not a bare knowledge or iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the vnderſtanding onely, but a naturall power, facultie, or created qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie: from whence iudgement &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge doe proceede as effects. This the ſcriptures doe confirme, aſcribing ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie works and actions to conſcience, as accuſing, excuſing, comforting, terrifiing which could not proceede from thence, if it were no more then an naked and
<pb facs="tcp:17063:9"/>
bare action or act of the minde.</p>
            <p>Wherfore,<note place="margin">10 As conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is in all men &amp; Angels ſo doth it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply al prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the minde, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them.</note> it is that power of the ſoule whoſe propertie is to take the principall concluſions of the minde, and apply them either to accuſe or excuſe. So that this is the grounde of all, that Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is a thing which can neuer bee loſt, albeit the ſame may looſe the vſe for a time, as reaſon in a drunken man, for it is in all reaſonable creatures both man and Angell, as in the proper ſubiects. Therefore all conſciences that now doe ſleepe, ſhall once be wakened, eyther in mercie, or in iudgement, heere or in hel: for the torment of an euill conſcience in the wicked,<note place="margin">Eſa. 66.24</note> is a worme (ſaieth the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet) which ſhall neuer die, and a fire that ſhall neuer be quenched.</p>
            <p>The ende of conſcience is to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of things done,<note place="margin">11 The ende of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and wherein it differeth from other giftes and faculties of the mind.</note> whereby it diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth from all other gifts of the minde, as are intelligence, opinion, ſcience, faith, prudence, &amp;c. For as to intelligence, it ſimplie conceaueth a thing to be, or not be, opinion iudgeth a thing to be proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or contuigent. Science iudgeth it to be ſure and certaine: faith is a perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereby we beleeue things that are
<pb facs="tcp:17063:10"/>
not, but are hid from vs as yet, prudence diſcerneth what is meete to be done, or what to be left vndone. But Conſcience goeth further then all theſe, for it giueth ſentence of things done by ſaying vnto vs &amp; ſhewing vs, this was done, this was not done. This may be done. This may not be done. This was well done. This was euill done.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">12 3. things to be marked</note>Of Conſcience thus deſcribed, there doe ariſe three things to be marked.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſte, that the things wherof Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence determines, are a mans owne acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons only: (for to be certaine what any other man hath done or ſaid, is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called knowledge) but what a man himſelfe hath done or ſaid, belongeth to Conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Conſcience meddles not with generals: but dealeth onely in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular actions, and that not in a few but in all.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, that the maner of conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is a determination, to ſet downe her iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, either with the creature or againſt it, and that becauſe it is of diuine nature placed by God in our ſoules, betweene him and vs, as an arbitrator to giue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence,
<pb facs="tcp:17063:10"/>
and pronounce decreet, eyther with vs or againſt vs to God. For ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it conſents and ſpeaks with God, againſt perſons in whome it is placed: &amp; other times againe, it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſents with them, and ſpeaketh for them before the Lorde. Examples hereof, there bee manie in the Scriptures, as of the firſt ſort, <hi>Kain</hi> &amp; <hi>Iudas,</hi> and in the latter, <hi>Peter</hi> and the <hi>Theefe,</hi> who albeit their ſinnes were gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous, becauſe they repented, their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience aſſured them of mercie.</p>
            <p>And this is the cauſe why we call this effect of our minde Conſcience.<note place="margin">13 Why the <hi>Practical</hi> parte of the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is called con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note> For as <hi>Scire,</hi> to know, is of one man onely by himſelfe. So is <hi>Conſcire,</hi> when at the leaſt two know ſome ſecret thing. The which they doe both knowe together. Wherfore, the name <hi>Conſcientia,</hi> or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is that thing that maketh two to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether partakers or partners of the knowledge of things which are ſecret in the minde of men or Angels.</p>
            <p>Now it is certaine,<note place="margin">14 God and man are partners onely in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of conſcience</note> that in this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge with man of his ſecrete deedes &amp; thoughts, no creatures can be partners with him (becauſe neither men nor An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels doe know mans thoughts &amp; ſecrets,
<pb facs="tcp:17063:11"/>
vnleſſe the ſame be reuealed vnto them) and therefore it remaineth, that in the knowledge therof, conſcience hath God onely to be partner with man in all his thoughts, words, and deeds, how ſecret ſoeuer they be: and man againe, by the gift of God, doth know the ſame of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, together with God in his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. And thus far concerning the word Conſcience, and the difinition thereof, The which heere Saint Iohn calleth the <hi>hearte of man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 What a griefe is a troubled conſcience Prouer. 18.14.</note>It followeth, to ſpeake next of the greefe of a troubled Conſcience, which of all others is moſt intollerable. For the ſpirit of man (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) wil ſuſteine his infirmitie, but a wounded ſpirite, who can beare it? That is, a troubled &amp; a wounded conſcience, is of al greefe the greateſt, &amp; the greeuouſeſt puniſhment that God at any time layeth vpon either man or Angell. So that men to be ridde out of this torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, doe chuſe oftentimes rather death, then to liue vnder the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable and intollerable greife thereof, albeit in all other troubles, they be able to indure even vnto the ende therof, yet this onely is that griefe which they can
<pb facs="tcp:17063:11"/>
no waies ſuſtaine. As examples, both of prophane and diuine hiſtories doe beare recorde. For whether we conſider this greefe in them who are meere naturall men, and neuer knewe God in Chriſt, or in them that are renewed by the holie Ghoſte, and ſpirit of regeneration, wee ſhal finde it to bee in either of them, the greateſt griefe &amp; torment of all others.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt ſorte, whether the ſame <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> be heathen people, who neuer knewe Gods word, or elſe ſuch as in true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion did not rightly, but ſuperſtitiouſlie worſhip God, wee ſhall perceaue if wee liſt to reade hiſtories, that this wound of an accuſing heart, and troubled ſpirite, coulde not bee healed with any medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, or other comforte whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>For the hethen Philoſophers, the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified"/> of all others among the Gentles, as <hi>Cato</hi> and others, who did beare all trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles moſt patiently, to the great admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all the world, did yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, where their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences became troubled, and when ſome great diſtreſſe of minde wounded their heart and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, make an ende of their liues with their owne handes. Some by drinking deadlie
<pb facs="tcp:17063:12"/>
poyſon. Some by running themſelues vo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>luntarily, vpon the weapons of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemis. Some by caſting themſelues from hie places vnto the deepe of the ſea, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer high rocks, to beate and ſtrike them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues all to peeces. And ſome not ſtick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſtogge themſelues through the harts with ſwords, knyues, or other ſuch weapons, for griefe of this wound of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, &amp; trouble of heart, all the which perſones, ſo long as other waies their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces were not ſurcharged, &amp; ouermai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered, were in al bodilie troubles invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible, &amp;c. As <hi>Cato, Iaſſon</hi> the husband of <hi>Medea, Lucretia,</hi> and others. As <hi>Alexander</hi> the greate and <hi>Nero,</hi> who would haue put hand to themſelues for greefe of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The like we may beholde in perſons, that either ſuperſticiouſly worſhip God, as Papiſts, or yet in the common ſort of people, that in mouth profeſſe Chriſt, but yet in works doe deny him, who are all caſt into the ſpirite of ſlumbering, num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes or hardnes of hart, who hearing, hear not, nor ſeeing cannot perceaue, but are ſenſles and blockiſh, vnto the time that God doth looſe the brydle of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences,
<pb facs="tcp:17063:12"/>
and ſetteth before them their ſinnes committed, and the puniſhmente due vnto them. Then may we ſee in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, how greeuouſly they are tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, and what ſorrowfull ends they doe make, while ſome of them doe hang themſelues. Some drowne themſelues. Some cutte their owne throtes, &amp; ſome of them doe ſtogge themſelues to the hearts, with kniues, daggers, or ſwordes: And all to rid themſelues out of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable and feareful griefe of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as they doe falſly ſuppoſe, vnto whome <hi>Iudas</hi> and <hi>Kain,</hi> are fearefull pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons and teachers. As to that wicked Spaniyard <hi>Alphonſus</hi> who when he could not by any meanes diſſwade his brother <hi>Diaſius</hi> by faire meanes from the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the goſpell, to embrace Papiſtrie,<note place="margin">anno. 1551</note> hee cruellie murthered him. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore greeued in Conſcience, there after did hang himſelfe at the councel of <hi>Trent.</hi> The like alſo did <hi>Robert Long,</hi> a man at armes in <hi>Calice,</hi> a falſe witnes againſt <hi>William Smyth</hi> preacher,<note place="margin">anno, 15<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> who grieued in conſcience therefore, did immediately thereafter runne to the water and drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned himſelfe. So heauie lay that ſinne of
<pb facs="tcp:17063:13"/>
falſe witneſſe bearing vpon his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. And what ſhall wee ſay of <hi>George Brodway,</hi> ſuborned by the councell of <hi>Calice,</hi> about the ſame time to beare al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo falſe witnes againſt <hi>Thomas Brooke;</hi> Who therefore went about to cutte his owne throate for griefe of conſcience, &amp; when he was ſtayed to doe the ſame, and the knyfe taken from him, wherewith he had wounded himſelfe, he became ſtark madde and ſo dyed. Sir <hi>Iames Halles</hi> alſo Knight, and iuſtice of the common place for greefe of conſcience that he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the knowen trueth, and embraced papiſtrie, at Queene <hi>Maries</hi> commande, drowned himſelfe. <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeuenth (as witneſſeth <hi>Benno</hi>) dyed deſperatlie at <hi>Salernum</hi> of the onely greefe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: vnto whome we may adde <hi>Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Eckins</hi> and <hi>Thomas Blaverus Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> who all miſerablie and in deſperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ended this life for onley griefe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and who liſt to read moe of this number, and of all ſortes both of men &amp; women, he ſhall finde many that miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rablie for griefe of conſcience in deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration haue ended their liues in that booke which is intituled <hi>Hiſtoria Tragica.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17063:13"/>
Therefore of all burthens, the griefe of conſcience is the greateſt.</p>
            <p>But heere the queſtion may bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded,<note place="margin">5 Queſtion.</note> why ſome of all theſe ſortes of people do diſpatch the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelus of this life by ſo violent death, and ſome others againe do dye ſo quiet, or rather ſenceleſly with out griefe?</p>
            <p>Anſwere,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> that the cauſe is in reſpecte that ſome feeling no ſinne in this life, do departe like drunken and brutiſh ſwine and waken not out of their helliſh ſleepe vntill they be in hell, and the tormentes thereof fully ſeaſe vpon them.<note place="margin">Some are ſurcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the deadly ſleepe of ſinne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end of their life and vthers overbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened with ſinne are waken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this life throgh the weight thereof.</note> And the others being ſurcharged, &amp; ouerburthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with ſinne in this life, doe dye like barking madde dogges in deſperation, without Chriſt and true repentance with <hi>Kain, Iudas, Iulian</hi> the Apoſtate and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Of theſe two ſortes there bee moſt of the firſte in this laſt age, wherein Chriſt ſhal finde no faith at his comming but all perſons for the moſte parte, ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in that deadly ſecurity, wherin they ſhall aſſure themſelues of peace, when as nothing is neearer hand vnto them then fearefull and endleſſe torment of conſcience, the worme whereof ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:17063:14"/>
die, &amp;c. Wherfore the Lord (as ſaith the Apoſtle) commandeth all ſuch to waken and ryſe vp from the ſleepe of ſinne by faith, repentance, and holie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, that while they haue time, Chriſt may giue them light.</p>
            <p>Thus much touching the griefe of conſcience, both in the heathen and alſo in the prophane and ſuperſtitious profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of Religion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we finde that the tormente of Conſcience,<note place="margin">1 Examples of Gods children. Conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is a wound which no Phyſitian can heale</note> euen in Gods children, &amp; in ſuch as are renewed with his ſpirit, is a greefe intollerable, and ſo greate, both in all Chriſts members, vpon whome it is layde, and alſo in their head Chriſt him ſelfe, that it is heauier then a thouſande deaths, and yet no wayes to be relieued with any comforte, or ſolace vnder the heauen, as all other griefes may bee, bee they neuer ſo great: for example, let vs take <hi>Iob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 3.</note> who for the loſſe of all his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, authoritie, children, and health of body, neuer ſhrunk nor quailed, vntil his vnhappy friends wounded his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and then he affirmed and compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that God had faſtened in him ſharp arrowes, ſette him as a butte to ſhute at,
<pb facs="tcp:17063:14"/>
and made him to poſſeſſe the ſinnes of his youth. So heauie a burthen was this wounded hearte and Conſcience vnto him, who vnder all other troubles, was a patterne of al vprightnes and patience, neuer beeing mooued therewith anie thinge at all (as it were) vntill this griefe did prick him.</p>
            <p>The like may we alſo beholde in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others of the peculiar ſeruantes of God, as in <hi>Dauid, Ezechias,</hi> and <hi>Ieremie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2</note> who neuer did faint vnder any griefe, (notwithſtanding of all their infinite troubles) but onely vnder the burthen of a wounded Conſcience, wherwith when they felte themſelues ſurcharged, they then were like Cranes chattering, Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows mourning, and Pellicants caſting out fearefull cryes. So that with mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning like Doues, their hearts did cleaue to the duſte, and their tounges to the roofe of their mouthes.</p>
            <p>Yea, euen the Lorde our Maiſter and Sauiour Chriſt,<note place="margin">3</note> the true Image of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, God and man, when in his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode he felt this wound (his Godhead, lurking for the time) albeit vnder all his other troubles, which hee ſuſtained for
<pb facs="tcp:17063:15"/>
our ſakes he was couragious: yet heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in feeling his fathers wrath for our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, the which for them he was to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taine, he complained, <hi>that his ſoule was heauie vnto the death,</hi> and earneſtly prayed, <hi>that if it were posſible, that that cuppe ſhould paſſe away from him,</hi> which was ſo bitter, that while he prayed, hee ſweate bloud, and before he departed this life, pitefully cryed three ſeuerall times, that God had forſaken him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">What a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>efe is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oubled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</note>Of theſe premiſes, al men may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that are not a ſleepe vnto euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting condemnation, what a thing it is to poſſeſſe a grieued condemning heart, or troubled Conſcience. For there is no ſick<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, which is not vnto death, but Phyſick is provided, or may be had for it: no ſore, but Chirurgerie wil aforde a ſalue for it. Friendſhip helpeth pouertie, hope of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie impriſonment, ſute and fauour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer men from baniſhment, and time and authority weares away reproch: But none of all theſe or any other thing in all the earth, can helpe a troubled condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning heart, or a wounded Conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4</note>Where by the contrary, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of a ſafe Conſcience &amp; quyet heart or mind,
<pb facs="tcp:17063:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
doth helpe, heale, and cure, all the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, griefes, and troubles, that can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall eyther men or women.<note place="margin">Pro. 15.15</note> For it is ſaith <hi>Salomon, a continuall feaſte,</hi> and a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſolace in al the greateſt troubles &amp; griefes in the worlde: yea, this ſame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in health and in good caſe, will vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly ſuſtaine and eaſily beare all other troubls whatſoeuer: but if it be troubled nothing is able to ſuſtaine that griefe. Studie therefore aboue all thinges,<note place="margin">Prouerb. 18.14.</note> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyde the teſtimonie of an euill Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and to gette, keepe, and entertaine the precious iewell of a good Conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, which wil neuer ſuffer them who poſſeſſe the ſame to bee afrayde of euil tydings, (ſaith the Prophet) for if wee acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and confeſſe our ſinnes,<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 7.8. Pſal. 51.1.</note> he is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and iuſt, who hath promiſed to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue vs them, and to cleanſe vs from all vnrighteouſnes in the bloud of his Chriſt Let vs therefore iudge and condemne our ſelues, confeſſe our wickednes, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent vs of our ſins, that our owne hearts condemne vs not before the Lorde our God, for he will neuer, but both accuſe vs and condemne vs, where our Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="tcp:17063:16"/>
doth the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5 Conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in hell what a griefe.</note>Wee haue heere to marke, that if the griefe of Conſcience bee ſo grieuous a thing to ſuſtaine in this life, how much more grieuous is it to be ſuffered in hel, where there is no redemption, neither ſhal the torments thereof haue any end, where the worme thereof ſhall not dye, nor yet the fire that ſhall torment it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be quenched. Take heede to this, all Epicures and Athieſts, and who ſay that hell is made, and ordained to feare but children and young folkes withall, who yet might ſee if they were not blind, the beginning of hell in the troubled Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of the wicked euen in this life, to to be a thing intollerable, and yet much more ſhall it be ſo in the life to come, in reſpect both that the torments thereof ſhall bee infinite degrees augmented, &amp; likewiſe continue &amp; indure for euer and without end.<note place="margin">6 Eſa. 28.15. Queſtion.</note> But ſome there be (ſaith the Prophet) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do ever put from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the euil day of the Lord, and haue made a coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with death, and a league with hell, that albeit a ſcourge runne ouer &amp; paſſe through, it ſhall not come at them, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of falſhood and vanitie, wherewith
<pb facs="tcp:17063:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
they haue cloaked and hid themſelues.</p>
            <p>Anſwer, that ſuch,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> albeit they haue no outward croſſe nor trouble in this life, yet ſhall they neuer eſcape a wounded Conſcience, eyther in this life or in that to come, for al the wicked the more they flee from it (although Gods children by faith and repentance doe often eſcape it the more it perſeweth them, and once fearefully ſhall ouertake them, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them of all their ſins, convict them, condemne them, and execute Gods ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible iudgement of vnſpeakeable tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt them, whereof there ſhall neuer be an ende. For this is that worme that neuer ſhall dye, and the fire of hell which burneth with it,<note place="margin">7 Epheſ. 5.14 The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the firſte parte.</note> that neuer ſhalbe quenched. Let vs therfore <hi>Watch &amp; pray,</hi> awake &amp; ſtand vp from the dead while we haue time, who hytherto haue ſleped and ſnored in all kinde of ſinne and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie, that we fall not into this gulfe of torment of a condemning heart &amp; trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled ſpirit of euill Conſcience, with the moſte part of this vnhappie age, that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer will awake and repent before they bee wakened with the tormentes of hels fire, in the miſerable and endles life to
<pb facs="tcp:17063:17"/>
come. For it is aboue all things, the due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of all ſuch as are carefull of their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, earneſtly, and continually, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſeaſing, to praye and call vnto the Lord, that hee in his Chriſte may giue vs light through faith, repentance and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendement of our euill ſpent liues, that we perriſh not with the wicked worlde, which ſleepeth ſecurely in all kinde of miſchiefe, without remorſe or griefe of Conſcience, and wil ſo do vnto the ende, to their intollerable puniſhment &amp; miſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie, that neuer ſhall haue ende.</p>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>The Second parte.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1</note>HAuing declared in the firſt part of our diuiſion, the ſence &amp; meaning of the Apoſtle, what is the definition of conſcience, as alſo what an intollerable burthen is the griefe of a wounded con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Two due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</note>It reſteth to ſpeak of the proper due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and actions of Conſcience, which are of two ſortes: to wit, eyther to beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and giue teſtimonie, or elſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce ſentence &amp; giue iudgement, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with vs or againſt vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17063:17"/>It beareth witneſſe or giueth teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,<note place="margin">2</note> when it telleth vs that a thinge was done or not done of vs. For the Apoſtle ſaith, that the Gentils did ſhew the effect of the law, written in their hearts, their Conſcience alſo bearing witnes,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.15.</note> &amp; their thoughts accuſing one another, or excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</p>
               <p>And againe he ſayth,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.12.</note> that his reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing is the teſtimonie of his Conſcience, that in ſimplicity and godlie purenes, he had his conuerſation in the world, &amp;c Where we haue to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, firſt of what things is it that conſcience beareth wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: ſecondly in what maner:<note place="margin">3 Three thinges to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</note> &amp; thirdlie how long.</p>
               <p>As to the firſt, it beareth witnes and record of all our thoughts, affections, &amp; actions. For we vſe to proteſt ſometimes in our conſciences, that we neuer thoght ſomething, let be to haue done it. It bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth alſo witneſſe, what our wils and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections be in all matters,<note place="margin">Rom. 9.1.</note> as <hi>I ſay the trueth in Chriſte, I lye not, my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence bearing mee vvitneſſe by the holie Ghoſte.</hi> Thirdly, (<hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith) that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten our heart or conſcience knoweth, that we haue curſed others,<note place="margin">Eccle. 7.24</note> that is ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17063:18"/>
euill of them.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">How con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience bea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note>2 The manner that Conſcience vſeth in giuing teſtimonie or bearing witneſſe ſtandeth in two things. To wit, firſt, it ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerueth and taketh knowledge of all thinges which wee doe. 2. It doeth tell vs inwardly and ſecreetely within our hearts of them all, and ſo it is like vnto a noater, who hath euer a pen in his hand to write and put into his protocoll, whatſoeuer is ſaid or done by vs ſo long as we liue.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">4 Conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce beareth witnes for euer.</note>Thirdly, It beareth vs witnes not for any ſhort ſpace of time, but for euer, both in this life, and in the life to come. So that when man dyeth, his Conſcience dyeth not: yea, when we ſhall ryſe againe, our Conſcience ſhall come with vs to the barre of Gods iudgements, eyther to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe vs, or excuſe vs before God: for the Apoſtle ſayteh,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.15.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Their Conſciences bearing them witneſſe, at the day when GOD ſhall iudge the ſecreits of men by Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">5 Three thinges to be learned</note>Of this duety of conſcience we learne three things: firſt, that there is a God; for ſeeing it beareth witneſſe of all our thoghts, vnto the which neither man nor Angell is priuie. It muſt needs therefore
<pb facs="tcp:17063:18"/>
be that it is to God alone, (who ſeeth &amp; knoweth all things) to whome our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience beareth witneſſe and record. And therefore, let Athieſts &amp; godles perſones barke againſt this as long as they liſt, yet haue they that within them, to wit, their conſcience (the which will conuince and conuict them of the trueth of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, will they, or nill they, eyther in life or in death, and that he hath ſtore of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and of infernall ſpirits to punniſh them in the ende. For many Examples heereof, one ſhal ſerue. A certaine Skof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer and filthie geſter, who this way gate for the moſte parte, all his liuing, was in a Tauerne, where manie were drinking, and there to play thee ſporter, did mock the immortalitie of the ſoule, and offered to ſell his ſoule (if any he had) to them that would giue him an kanne of wine for it. The which, when one of them that were drinking there had bought from him, &amp; giuen to him the ſaid Kan of wine: Sathan in mans likenes, adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning himſelfe to the Table, with them that were in the Tauerne, and deſired to haue the ſoule of this geſter, of the ſame price of him that had bought it. The par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:17063:19"/>
who firſt bought it, granted therevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and deliuered it vnto him as hee had it for another Kanne of wine. The which when hee had deliuered, hee tooke him from the Table both body and ſoule. See more of this hiſtorie, and of the like in <hi>Hiſtoria tragica.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">The proui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dence of God ouer all men: whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſience will not ſuffer them to hide any thing from them.</note>2 We learne heerby, that God doth watch ouer all men by a ſpeciall proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, in that he giueth to euery man a particular Conſcience to bee his watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man &amp; keeper, who in this poynte is like vnto a maſter of priſon, who giueth to his priſoners keepers to watch the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; to bring them home againe into the priſon if at anie time they purchaſe his licence to goe abroad for their particular turns: Euen ſo haue all men and women Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences to follow them alwaies as at the heeles and to dog them, and to trye all their thoughts, words, works, and affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and to beare recorde, and true witnes thereof to God, and vnto their owne hearts. In ſuch ſorte, that although we may hide our turnes from men, yet is it certaine that our Conſcience will ſhew them all before God.</p>
               <p>Therefore, we ought to ſtand aboue al
<pb facs="tcp:17063:19"/>
things to do vprightly, and to follow the word of God in all that we doe, or leaue vndone (which is the onely ſquare and rule of our Conſcience) that the ſame may excuſe vs, and not accuſe vs before our God, for if our heart accuſe vs to our God, God is farre greater then our harts to condemne vs, but if not, then we may haue bouldnes towards him.</p>
               <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">The good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of god in ſetting our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to tell vs what to doe, &amp; vnder wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> paines. 1 Cor. 12.13.</note> we obſerue heere the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and loue of God toward vs, who ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth our Conſcience to tell vs ſecretly when we doe amiſſe, to the ende that we ſhould preſently repente vs thereof and amend, that he may forgiue vs, but if not that then oppenly it ſhould accuſe vs thereof before God, and at the barre of his iudgement ſeate, before al his Angels and ſaints in heauen. Wherefore wee ſhould accuſe and condemne our ſelues heere, that we be not accuſed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned there, if we deſire to be ſaued in that great day of the Lord. For if we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe and convict our ſelues when we doe amiſſe, with repentance &amp; amendeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, neither ſhall our conſcience accuſe vs to our God, nor he condemne vs for the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill which we haue committed. And thus
<pb facs="tcp:17063:20"/>
much touching the firſt duety of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which ſtandeth in witnes-bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to God in accuſing or excuſing vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">6 The iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of Conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce what.</note>As to the ſecond action or worke of Conſcience, it is to giue iudgement of things which we haue done, and ſo it is like a iudge, cauſing malefactours to be arraigned at the barre of his iudgement ſeate, and there to ſuffer for their deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites: yea, rather it is like a little God, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the middle of mans heart, araig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and iudging him in this life, as hee ſhal be arraigned and iudged for his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences at the tribunall ſeate of the Lord God in the day of iudgement. So that that iudgement giuen in this life by conſcience, is nothing elſe but a certaine and ſure fore-runner of the laſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to come.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">7 We are ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moniſhed of two thinges. 1. Iob<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3.20</note>We are admoniſhed heereby to take heede, that nothing paſt lye vpon vs, and that we charge not our Conſciences in time comming with any matter whereof they may accuſe vs. For if our conſcience ſhall accuſe vs, much more ſhall God condemne vs. Becauſe he both ſeeth all our doings more clearely then doe our Conſciences, &amp; iudgeth more ſincerely
<pb facs="tcp:17063:20"/>
and ſecretly then they can do vnto vs. Therefore wee ought to endeuour our ſelues with <hi>Paull,</hi> to ſay alwaies,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.4.18.</note> that we knowe nothing by our ſelues in our life, that wee may euer ſtand in our Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence without blame before him.</p>
               <p>Heere we muſt conſider two thinges.<note place="margin">8 Two thinges to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</note> Firſt, the cauſe that maketh Conſcience to giue iudgement, and ſecondly, the maner how it giueth i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. The cauſe is the onely binder of Conſcience, which is ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proper or improper.</p>
               <p>The proper binder of Conſcience is Gods law,<note place="margin">9 Acts. 4. Rom. 13.</note> and the improper the lawes of Princes, hauing their authority of God to make ſuch lawes for the good of their ſubiects, as ar agreeable with his law, or otherwaies, they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not binde Conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Wher we learne that gods word is euer to be obeyed,<note place="margin">10 Gods worde e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to be o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beyed.</note> albeit thereby we ſhoulde offend all men, and alſo looſe our owne liues. Becauſe wee are bound and obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed thereto in Conſcience.</p>
               <p>Secondly, wee muſt take heede,<note place="margin">11 What wee ought to take heede vnto.</note> that that which we take in hand to doe, haue a warrant in our Conſcience out of the word to doe it: &amp; ſuch like that which we leaue vndone, if we may leaue it vndone without the wound of conſcience or not.
<pb facs="tcp:17063:21"/>
As for example. The knowledge of God and his worde bindeth vs to learne it in Conſcience, albeit the knowledge of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſcience doth not the like, &amp;c. For all perſons are bound in Conſcience to know God aright,<note place="margin">We are bounde chiefely in conſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence to know two things. 12</note> &amp; as he hath reuealed himſelfe to the world in his word, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially theſe two things. Firſt, that all perfite righteouſnes and life euerlaſting is to be obtained in Chriſt. And ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the inſtruments to obtaine the ſame righteouſnes and life in Chriſt, is onely faith.</p>
               <p>It followeth, to ſhew how Conſcience giueth iudgement of all our doings: to wit, by a kind of reaſoning, called a <hi>Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall</hi> ſyllogyſme, wherein Conſcience vſeth two inſtruments in making of this reaſon, which are <hi>minde</hi> and <hi>memorie.</hi> For the <hi>minde</hi> telleth Conſcience, what the Law of God is, and <hi>memorie</hi> bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to her <hi>minde</hi> all the particuler acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that men or women haue done or not done, that Conſcience may deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and giue iudgement thereof. So that from theſe two, the Conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoneth after this maner, as for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. The Conſcience of a whoremonger
<pb facs="tcp:17063:21"/>
reaſoneth thus with himſelfe, ſaying. All whoremoungers ſhall be without in the fierie lake, that burneth with fire &amp; brim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtone, which is the ſecond death. But I am a whoremounger. Therefore, I ſhall be there.</p>
               <p>So that hereby we ſee that the ſinnes,<note place="margin">13</note> and conpunctions of the heart, are ſore and grieuous prickes vnto the minde &amp; Conſcience of man, yea, greater then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny griefe that can befall him. Although Sathan for a time doeth extenuate the ſame, as alſo corrupt affections doe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes ſo ouercaſt this iudgement,<note place="margin">Gen. 42.21.</note> that it perceaueth nothing for the ſpace of a long time: as <hi>Ioſephs</hi> bretheren, who were blinded this way for the ſpace of two &amp; and twentie yeares or thereby.<note place="margin">2. Sam. 24.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his murther &amp; adulterie, ſlept with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out remorſe, vntill he was wakened by the Prophet <hi>Nathan,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 2.37.</note> and the Iewes, who put Chriſt to death, vntil they were pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with <hi>Peters</hi> ſermon.</p>
               <p>The effects of an accuſing Conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce are eſpecially fiue, 1. <hi>Griefe,</hi> 2. <hi>Sadnes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">14 Iſa. 17.20 Pro. 28.1, 2. Cor. 1.12. Pro. 15.15. Pro. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.18.</note> 3. <hi>Feare,</hi> 4. <hi>Perturbation</hi> of the whole man, &amp; 5. <hi>Deſperation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This much of the accuſing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning
<pb facs="tcp:17063:22"/>
Conſcience. Now haue wee to ſpeake of the Conſcience excuſing and abſoluing, which hath all things contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the accuſing and condemning, as <hi>Bouldnes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 15.15</note> 
                  <hi>ioy</hi> in the <hi>Holie-Ghoſte, Confidence</hi> with aſſurance of mercy. <hi>For the righteous</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon) are boulde as a Lyon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">15</note>Learne heere reader, that what is done of a doubting, or of an erronious Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,<note place="margin">To doubt, erre, or do any thing againſt conſcience is ſinne. Ro. 14.23. &amp;. 14.14.</note> or againſt Conſcience is ſinne. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, <hi>vvhatſoeuer is not of faith is ſinne,</hi> and to the vncleane all things are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eleane. Some did iudge fornication in the Primitiue Church not to bee ſinne, wherein notwithſtanding they ſinned, in reſpect that their Conſcience did erre in her iudgement: For euill remains euill, albeit Conſcience ſaith the contrarie a thouſand times. Moſte men &amp; women are ſicke of this diſeaſe at this day, who thinke ſin not to bee ſinne in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, &amp;c. What is done alſo againſt Conſcience, is ſin in the doer, albeit it erre and be deceaued.<note place="margin">16 What ſhould be our war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in all our turnes</note>
               </p>
               <p>Of al this, let vs learne to obſerue for a warrant to our Conſciences, the onely command or contremand of Gods word in all our proceedings, and ſo ſhall wee
<pb facs="tcp:17063:22"/>
walke ſurely when, wee make his worde the onely rule to our Conſcience, &amp; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chew mans inuentions, or good intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: and likewiſe, when we vnderſtande that it is a moſte dangerous and deadly thing, to bee ignorant of the knowledge of Gods word, which maketh the life of man to abound: yea, to flow with the ſea of al offences againſt God. And there fore, we ſhuld euer pray him of his great mercie, to graunt vs aboue al things, the true knowledge of him and of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, with the teſtimony of an ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuſing and vpright Conſcience, ruled e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer by the ſquare of his worde, in the which, righteouſnes and eternall life is onely to be found throgh faith in Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>The Thirde parte.</head>
               <p>Two parts of our diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of. It followeth,<note place="margin">1 the diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on touch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing the kindes &amp; ſortes of Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces.</note> thirdly to intreate of the kindes and ſortes of Conſciences, &amp; in ſpecial, firſt of the Conſcience of the regenerate, and of all Gods children: &amp; ſecondly of that of the wicked.</p>
               <p>For as to Conſcience generally,<note place="margin">2</note> it is eyther good or bad, and a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb facs="tcp:17063:23"/>
is that which rightly and according to Gods word excuſeth and comforteth.<note place="margin">Conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is either good or bap &amp; the excel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie thereof conſiſteth in excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wng.</note> So that the excellencie of Conſcience ſtandeth in excuſing &amp; not in accuſing, by reaſon that when we commit any ſin, we giue then occaſion immediatly ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, to our Conſcience to accuſe and condemne vs, wherby we doe wound &amp; hurt the ſame: as teſtifieth the Apoſtle, ſaying,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 8.9.12,</note> that the <hi>Corinthians</hi> did wound the Conſciences of their weake brethren, when they vſed their liberty as an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of offence to them. And againe, hee calleth a good Conſcience, a conſcience without offence, or accuſing of them that haue it.<note place="margin">Act. 24.16.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, a good Conſcience is of two ſorts:<note place="margin">3 Good con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience of two ſortes by creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and rege<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neration.</note> to wit, eyther good by creation, or elſe by regeneration. The conſcience of our firſt pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts before their fal, was good onely by creation, &amp; therfore could not but excuſe them before God in all that they did in the eſtate of their innocency</p>
               <p>A good Conſcience regenerat, is that which being corrupt by nature, is renu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and purged by faith in the bloud of Chriſte,<note place="margin">4</note> in all ſuch there is a conuerſion or change needefull by grace, becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:17063:23"/>
by nature all mens conſciences through ſinne are euill, and therfore become good onely by grace in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The inſtrumentall cauſe ſeruing to make this change is faith,<note place="margin">5 Two cauſe of a good conſcience</note> which purifieth the hearts, and the meritorious cauſe, is the bloud of Chriſt, which doth purge conſciences from dead works, to ſerue the liuing God.</p>
               <p>A regenerat conſcience hath two pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties and ſtayes. To wit,<note place="margin">6 Two pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties or ſtayes of a regenerat conſcience</note> Chriſtian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and certaintie of ſaluation at all times, when ſhe excuſeth. Becauſe that theſe two propertis haue not their place in the outward man, but in the heart, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit or conſcience.</p>
               <p>I call Chriſtian liberty,<note place="margin">7 Chriſtian liberty what Gal 5.1.</note> the holie and ſpiritual freedome purchaſed vnto vs by Chriſt, wherin the Apoſtle commandeth vs to <hi>Standfaſt,</hi> and not to bee entang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againe with the yoake of bondage, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>It hath three partes.<note place="margin">8 Chriſtian liberty hath three parts.</note> As freedome from the iuſtification of the morrall law, and the fulfilling thereof. For hee who is a member of Chriſte, is not bound in Conſcience, to bringe the perfite
<pb facs="tcp:17063:24"/>
righteouſnes of the law in his owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for his iuſtification before God, but Chritſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">9</note>He alſo who is a Chriſtian, is free from the curſe and condemnation of the law, for to ſuch as are in Chriſt, <hi>There is no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 3 13.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe he hath redeemed them from the curſe of the Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">10</note>The ſecond, is the freedome and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that we haue by Chriſte from the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of the law, which craueth perfite obedience, and condemneth all imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, <hi>But ſinne hath no more dominion ouer them that are in Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ro. 6.14. Gal 3.13. 1. Ioh. 5.3.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe they are not vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the Law,</hi> or rigour thereof <hi>but vnder grace, and in Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">11</note>And therefore it is, that God accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth our imperfite obedience, if it be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere: yea, and as the Prophet ſayth, <hi>Will for worke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 3.16. 12</note> and <hi>Deſire for Deed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third is, freedome from the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall law. For after that the truth of all thoſe ſhadowes is come wee are no more vnder the ſhadowes to keepe and obſerue the ſame, which ſerued to the Iewes as a ſchoole-maiſter,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.25. Ephe. 2.15 Gal. 3.14.</note> to lead them to Chriſt, who was to come: but we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the truth, to wit, Chriſt, who is alrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>die
<pb facs="tcp:17063:24"/>
come, and hath ſuffered for vs in the fleſh, haue no neede now of thoſe types and ſhadowes of the ceremoniall law. Thus much concerning the firſt ſtay and property of a regenerate Conſcience.<note place="margin">13 The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d propertie or ſtay of a regenerat Conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce Rom 8.15. Epheſ. 4.13 Math. 14, 31. &amp;. 21.21. Iames 1.6 Ro. 8.20.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond property or ſtay of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate Conſcience (eſpecially when this ſame excuſeth) is an infalliable cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie of our ſinnes to be pardoned, and of life euerlaſting, by faith in Chriſt, wrought in our hearts by his ſpirit, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of al the ſcriptures of God beare witnes, that are heere vnder written, againſt that deſperate doctrine of the Biſhoppe of <hi>Rome,</hi> and Councell of <hi>Trent.</hi> As <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Math.</hi> 14.31. <hi>Math.</hi> 21.21. <hi>Iames.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.20. Therefore it is, that <hi>Baſilius</hi> demandeth this queſtion: What is the property of faith? To the which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund he anſwereth, that it is to be one aſſured perſwaſion voyde of doubting &amp; diſputation.</p>
               <p>Of theſe places of Scripture aboue mentioned,<note place="margin">14</note> let euery chriſtian make this reaſon to wit: Euery one that beleeueth is the child of God: but I beleeue: I ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore am the childe of God, and Gods children muſt needs be ſaued. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:17063:25"/>
I cannot periſh: againſt the doctrine of the papiſts, who will haue vs to doubt of our Saluation, againſt the Scriptures of God, and Articles of our beliefe, which doe command euery man &amp; wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man both to ſay, I beleeue in God. In Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt his onely Son our Lord, who is God alſo equall with his father. In the holie Ghoſt, who is likewiſe God, &amp; the third perſon of the Godhead.<note place="margin">1. Ioh 3.2.</note> And final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, both to beleeue remisſion of our ſins and life euerlaſting. But to doubt and to beleeue, are words which importe contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diction. God commandeth vs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the remisſion of our ſinnes, &amp; life euerlaſting, through the merits &amp; death of Chriſt, in the Articles of our beliefe: &amp; the Pope and Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſe al ſuch for preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptuous perſons, as doe not continually doubt of the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their ſinnes, certaintie of Saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and life eternall. And therefore, the concluſion is true, that the Pope is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary to Chriſt, and conſequently, that ſame Antichriſt, the myſterie of whoſe i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquitie beganne, euen in the dayes of the Apoſtles, and which hath ſo increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſenſine, that in all the heads of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb facs="tcp:17063:25"/>
religion, his doctrine is repugnant vnto Chriſts: And in this point, directlie to the verie Articles of our Chriſtian be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe.</p>
               <p>It may bee demaunded heere by way of queſtion,<note place="margin">15 Queſtion. Anſwer. A good conſcience may both accuſe and excuſe at one time, but not in one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte.</note> if one and the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience may not both accuſe and excuſe Gods children at any one time.</p>
               <p>Anſwer, that it may: For elſe if our Conſcience ſhould not ſtill accuſe vs when wee doe amiſſe, then ſhoulde manie great ſinnes aſſaulte vs at once, &amp; make hauock of our ſoules. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee affirme, that it may both accuſe vs, and excuſe vs at one time, but not in one reſpect. For it excuſeth vs, in that it aſſureth vs that our perſons doe ſtand righteous before God, as cloathed and couered with the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt. And in reſpecte that we haue our deſire, and doe endeuoure ourſelues in the generall courſe of our whole life, to walke vprightlie and to pleaſe God. And yet neuertheleſſe, of this it muſte needs accuſe vs perpetually for our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ſlippes, and for the manifolde wants and imperfections that bee in all our good and beſte actions, by reaſon
<pb facs="tcp:17063:26"/>
whereof it telleth vs, perpetually in our care,<note place="margin">Luek, 17.</note> that we are vnprofitable ſeruants.</p>
               <p>Thus much of a good Conſcience.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">16 Euill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience what and why it is ſo called.</note>Now followeth an euill Conſcience, which is ſo called, partly, becauſe it is corrupted by originall ſinne, and partly by reaſon it is euill, that is, troubleſome and painefull to our ſence and feeling, as are vnto vs all other ſorrowes, cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities or miſeries whatſoeuer, which for this ſame cauſe are called likewiſe euils.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">17 The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie of an euil co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience is ever to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe. Luke. 5.8.</note>The propirtie of it is euer to accuſe &amp; condemne, and thereby to make them that haue it, affrayde of the preſence of God, and to flee from him as from their enemie. Example in our firſt parents &amp; in <hi>Peter,</hi> who falling downe at Chriſtes knees beſought him to goe from him, in reſpect his Conſcience toulde him, and accuſed him that he was a ſinfull man.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">18 Euill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is ether dead or waking.</note>Euill Conſcience is eyther dead or waking and ſtirring, the dead Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is that which (albeit it can but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe) lyeth commonly quyet, accuſing little or nothing at all, and that for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers cauſes: to witte, want of reaſon, ſtrength and force of wicked and fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affections, &amp; ignorance of Gods word
<pb facs="tcp:17063:26"/>
and reuealed will.</p>
               <p>A dead Conſcience hath two proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: the firſt is, to be benu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>med,<note place="margin">19 A dead conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce hath two proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Gen. 44.16.</note> vnfeeling or doſened, as that of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> brethren, for the ſpace of two and twentie yeares, or thereby. This raigneth in drowſie Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, luke-warme Goſpellers, and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill honeſt perſons, who liue without common ſlander to the goſpell. Of this kinde of Conſcience let vs take heede. For it is like to a wilde beaſt, who ſo long as it lyeth a ſleepe troubleth nothing, but when it awaks, flyeth into mens fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and deuoureth them. This is it that the Poets did call the <hi>Furies,</hi> becauſe it purſueth them that haue it, vnto death and deſperation.</p>
               <p>The ſecond property of a dead Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is,<note place="margin">20</note> to be <hi>feared</hi> or burnt (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaieth) <hi>with an hotte yron:</hi> that is, the Conſcience which is paſt all feeling in this life, and is neuer mooued with the remorſe of ſin thorowly, or to any purpoſe. And this is in the onely obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate wicked, and ſuch as are giuen <hi>vp in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a reprobate minde.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 2.15.</note> This ſhall be wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened at the day of death and laſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment by God, to accuſe and condemne
<pb facs="tcp:17063:27"/>
them that haue it, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bookes of the dead, both of the great and ſmall ſhalbe opened.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">21 A ſtirring conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce hath foure degrees. 1 Accuſeth for euil do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note>Laſtly, a ſtirring euil Conſcience doth eyther accuſe or excuſe, &amp; it hath foure ſeuerall degrees or differences. The firſt that accuſeth a man for doing euill, is an euill conſcience, albeit by occaſion or accident, it ſerueth to bee a preparation to grace by the goodnes of God: As the needle that draweth the thred through the cloath, by making a hole in the cloath, ſerueth to ſowe it alſo. For to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, is euer a defect, and was not in man by creation. And therefore is one of the foure degrees of an euill conſcience.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">22 2. accuſeth for well doing. 23 3. Excuſeth euill doing</note>The ſecond, is that which accuſeth for well doing, and is in Idolaters, as not to ſay or goe to Maſſe, accuſeth a Papiſt.</p>
               <p>The third, is that which excuſeth euil &amp; doing, is found likewiſe in Idolaters, who when they ſlay and burne the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, their eroneous conſcience excuſeth them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">24 4 Excuſeth wel doing in vnrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons.</note>The fourth and laſt, excuſeth well do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in carnal and vnregenerate perſons, Example in <hi>Abimeleck,</hi> not committing adulterie with <hi>Abrahams</hi> wife, which
<pb facs="tcp:17063:27"/>
was a thing morallie good in it ſelfe, but not in the vnregenerate perſon, whoſe ciuill good workes are nothing elſe but gliſtering ſinnes, and this Conſcience is but <hi>Carnall</hi> and not regenerate.<note place="margin">Ro, 14, 14,</note> For as to the cleane, by faith al things are cleane. So to the vncleane that want faith no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is cleane nor acceptable in Gods ſight, how good ſoeuer otherwaies the ſame be morally, becauſe the perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who lacketh faith in Chriſt, is vncleane and therefore cannot pleaſe God.</p>
               <p>Let vs therfore drawe neere vnto our God, with true and penitent hearts,<note place="margin">25</note> in aſſurance of faith (as ſaith the Apoſtle) being voyde of an euill conſcience, and waſhed in our bodies with pure water. For it is <hi>by faith that the iuſte doe liue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb 10, 22 Act. 15.9, Heb, 10, 38, 39,</note> the which wee muſt follow vnto the conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of our ſoule, that all our workes may be acceptable to our God through Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>The Fourth parte.</head>
               <p>FOr as much as hytherto wee haue ſhewed both what conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is,<note place="margin">1</note> what the troubles thereof are? As likewiſe,
<pb facs="tcp:17063:28"/>
what are both the actions and the kinds thereof. It remaineth fourthly, &amp; laſtlie, to ſhew what is mans duety concerning Conſcience, how hee may preuent the troubles thereof, and being troubled in his heart and ſpirit, how he may releeue his conſcience, and exoner the ſame of all the troubles and wounds wherewith it may be grieued in this life.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2 Mans due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is two fould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning conſcience</note>Mans firſt duetie is in this behalfe, to purchaſe and get a good conſcience, for by nature (ſeeing we are all the children of wrath) we haue it not. And his ſecond duetie is to keepe it well when he hath gotten it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">3 three thing are neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</note>For the getting of a good conſcience, three things are needefull: to wit, a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration to it. Secondly, the application of the remedy, and thirdly, prepared the reformation of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">6 Gal. 3.10, Preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what.</note>The preparation to it requireth the knowledge of the law, that thereby wee may vnderſtand what is good or euill. 2. The iudiciall ſentence therof, which tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs, that the curſe of God is deue to all men for euery ſinne: 3. An earneſt examination of our Conſcience by the law, that thereby wee may perceaue and
<pb facs="tcp:17063:28"/>
vnderſtand what is our eſtate before God, and vpon this duety, the Prophets doe ſtand very much. For heereby it is, that we come to the knowledge of our wretchednes &amp; miſerable eſtate before our God. Wherefore,<note place="margin">Lamen. 3.40.</note> (<hi>Ieremie</hi> ſaith) <hi>Let vs ſearch and trye our waies, and turne againe vnto the lord: &amp; Zephaniah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zepha, 2, 1</note> 
                  <hi>Gather your ſelues euen gather you, O nation, not worthy to be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, before the decree come forth, and yee bee as chaffe which paſſeth in a day, and before the fierce wrath of the Lord come vpon you, &amp;c.</hi> For <hi>the law is a yoake</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>That neither we nor our fathers, we are able to beare.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 15.10</note>
               </p>
               <p>Hereby all men and women may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily ſee,<note place="margin">5</note> that by nature we are moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, becauſe we are vnable in our own defaulte to doe the works of the Law, &amp; fulfill that obedience, which we owe of duetie to our God, and that therefore we abid naturallie accurſed. This our mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerable eſtate, when wee know it by the law, it bringeth forth in vs a ſorrow and griefe, in reſpect of the knowledge of the puniſhment for ſin, aryſing of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our dueties towards God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined in the lawe, &amp; of our inability to performe the ſame. And thus much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb facs="tcp:17063:29"/>
our preparation to obtaine and get a good Conſcience.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">6 The appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the reme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy.</note>2 The application or applying of the remedy whereby to heale our ſorrow &amp; griefe conceiued of our wretched eſtate, by the knowledge of the law (which is onely the bloud and merites of Chriſte, who for vs in his Conſcience felte Gods wrath, and the puniſhments of all our ſinnes) requireth two things, that is, the preaching of the goſpell and faith. For the goſpel is the hand of God the father, offering vnto vs grace &amp; mercy in chriſt.<note place="margin">Rom, 3.20 Rom, 10, 4 1, Cor, 1, 3, Gal. 3.24,</note> And faith is our hand, whereby wee lay holde on him, and receaue him with all his benefits. For as by the law commeth the knowledge of ſinne, ſo is the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes of God, by faith in Ieſus Chriſte, made manifeſt without the law, vnto al, and vpon all that beleeue. For hee is the ende of the Law, for righteouſnes to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one that beleeueth: and the ende of the law is, to iuſtifie them that obſerue it Wherefore, Chriſt hauing fulfilled it for vs, is <hi>made our righteouſnes, wiſedome, ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication &amp; redemption.</hi> This much of the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the remedy againſt the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, &amp; deſperation aryſing of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:17063:29"/>
of our miſerable eſtate by nature, when wee doe beholde the ſame in the and mirrour of the law.</p>
               <p>Where wee haue to learne,<note place="margin">7 two things needefull to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hende and keepe Chriſt.</note> that two things are moſt needefull for vs who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire truly to enioy and poſſeſſe this reme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy. The firſt is ſeriouſly to humble our ſelues before God for all our wants, and eſpecially for ſuch as lye open in our Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, accuſing and condemning of our ſelues before his holie maieſtie. For ſo ſhall we put Conſcience out of office, &amp; performe that work our ſelues in this life which Conſcience would performe to our eternal damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the life to come <hi>For if we iudge our ſelues</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>we ſhal not be iudged.</hi> 2. We muſt ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with grones and earneſt prayers, humblie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech the Lord for Chriſts ſake, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue vs our ſins, that ſo wee may be ſure of his fauour, and forgiuenes of them all. And becauſe that this humiliation ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in theſe two poyntes, there are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and ſure promiſes made by God vnto vs of grace, &amp; life euerlaſting in his worde (for <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaieth) <hi>Hee that hideth his ſinnes ſhall not proſper:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 28, 13,</note> 
                  <hi>but hee that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth and forſaketh them ſhall haue mercie.
<pb facs="tcp:17063:30"/>
and if wee acknowledge and confeſſe our ſinnes</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iohn) God is faithfull and iuſt to forgiue vs them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.9.</note> 
                  <hi>and waſh them al away</hi> from vs, with the bloud of his chriſt. For <hi>Gabri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell</hi> the Angell ſaid vnto the virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> (that her ſonne) Chriſts name, ſhould be called <hi>Ieſus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 1.21</note> 
                  <hi>Becauſe hee ſhould ſaue his people from their ſinnes.</hi> Wherefore it followeth, that <hi>there is no condemnation to them that are</hi> and <hi>beleeue in him,</hi> if they walke not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit. To all which perſons, aryſeth a certainty of Saluation. And conſequently, a reformation of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which is wrought in all ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons by the holie ghoſte, when the ſame ceaſeth to accuſe and terrifie them, and beginneth to excuſe them, and to teſtifie vnto them, that they are the children of God. The which thinge neuer faileth to anie that doe ſeriouſlie humble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and by earneſt prayer craue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and pardon of their ſinnes at Gods hands for Chriſts ſake.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">8 The riches &amp; pleaſurs of the faithfull, &amp; which they ſhuld euer ſeeke for, is a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note>This is the treaſure that far paſſeth all worldlie pleaſures, I would to God ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that the greateſt part of this vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py age, would be as careful to ſute and ſeeke for the ſame, as they are to hunte
<pb facs="tcp:17063:30"/>
after the tranſitory pleaſures of this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible fleſh: as honors, riches, &amp; other pleaſures worldly, which wil quickly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, but this ſhall euer abide as a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall and pleaſant feaſt, both heere &amp; in the world to come.<note place="margin">Pro. 15.15.</note> And thus much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning mans firſte duetie, againſt the getting of a good conſcience.</p>
               <p>As touching mans ſecond duety con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,<note place="margin">9 Mans ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note> it is to keepe it good when he hath ſo gotten it, &amp; to preuente the troubles therof by all meanes posſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. For it is no leſſe vertue to keepe a good Conſcience then to get it.</p>
               <p>In keeping of a good Conſcience,<note place="margin">10 Three thinges to be avoyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 1. ig-nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. Pro. 29 2. 2, Kings 17, 26,</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all things, three things are to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyded. To wit, ignorance, vnmortified affections, and worldly luſtes. As to the firſt, <hi>Salomon</hi> affirmeth, that the minde cannot bee good, that is the Conſcience of him that is without knowledge: yea it is ſaid, cap 17.2. Kings, that the people that dwelt in <hi>Samaria,</hi> were deuoured of Lyons and wilde beaſtes, becauſe they knew not the manner of the God of the Land. And againe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 95.10,</note> the Prophete <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, that ſuch as doe not knowe the voice of the Lorde, and his will and
<pb facs="tcp:17063:31"/>
wayes, doe erre in heart and ſoule, neuer enter into the Lords reſt. Likwiſe Chriſt himſelfe telleth vs, that they that knowe not the ſcriptures, doe but erre &amp; goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray. And againe, that this is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the world, that the light of Gods will declared in Chriſt being come into the world: men notwihſtanding loue ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther darknes,<note place="margin">Math, 22, 29, Rom. 1, 28</note> and to periſh therein, then the light, and to be ſaued thereby. And therefore ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>as they regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not to knowe GOD, euen ſo GOD deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered them vp into a reprobate minde, to doe thoſe thinges which are not conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and whereby they become full of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſnes.</hi> Yea, ignorance (ſaith <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi>) is the worke of the diuils inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> who would not haue vs to ſee the trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure, leaſt wee ſhould poſſeſſe the riches. And that this is the cauſe of all euill, that the ſcriptures hath not knowen.</p>
               <p>Of theſe premiſſes we ſee how needful it is aboue all things, for al that wil keep a good Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, to learn the knowledge of Gods word, the ignorance wherof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth &amp; breedeth in man &amp; woman, a loathſome ſea of all euils, whereby their miſerable Conſciences are drowned in a
<pb facs="tcp:17063:31"/>
loathſom ſink of all wretched miſery vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the day of their Death, when the Lord ſhal fearefully in his iuſtice wake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, to their perpetual ſhame and confuſion.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it is needefull to be vtterly <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> diſpleaſed alwaies with the ſinful affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our fleſh. As with wrath, anger,<note place="margin">Let vs bee diſpleaſed with ſinne and the luſtes of the fleſhe.</note> en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vie, malice, wandering luſtes, &amp; ſuch like other vnhappy fruits of our wretched &amp; corrupt nature. And therefore continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to crye with the Apoſtle. <hi>O wretched man that I am, who ſhal deliuer me from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of this death,</hi> or from this fleſhlie lumpe of ſinne and death, which by nature eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one of vs do carry about with vs. So that this way in our mind at the leaſt, we may euer ſerue the law of god,<note place="margin">Rom, 7, 25</note> &amp; ſo crop &amp; ſnedde ſinne in vs, that it come neuer to ſeede, maturity, and ful perfection, to raigne in vs and rule ouer vs aboue the Spirite.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, as to worldly pleaſures and honours of this life, let vs euer reſpecte them all as dunge in reſpecte of Chriſt, the benefites which wee receaue by him and the preſeruation of a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. The which wee ought perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie to eſteeme and thinke off, as of
<pb facs="tcp:17063:32"/>
of our Paradiſe, and of the luſtes of our fleſhe, and pleaſures of the world, as of the forbidden fruite, if we deſire to liue for euer with perpetuall ioy in our ſoule and conſcience, both in this life and in that to come through Chriſt. And thus much touching the keeping of a good conſcience when it is gotten.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> As to the remedies of a troubled hart and grieued Conſcience,<note place="margin">The reme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dies of a troubled conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</note> which of al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, when it rageth is the greateſt, wee ſay that the ſame muſt be ſought for out of the word, and exampels of the faithful as of <hi>Iob, Ieremy, Ezekiah, Dauid,</hi> &amp; alſo of Chriſt himſelfe, who felt the extremeſt anguiſh that euer eyther was, is, or yet ſhallbe, and notwithſtanding periſhed not there through, becauſe they diſpay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not therein, but truſted ſtil in God, and therefore were deliuered.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Such muſt vnderſtand as are trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in Conſcience, that the way to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, is euen to goe thither by hell.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">They that go to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, muſt ſaile by hell.</note>3 Let all ſuch as are in this trouble, haue recourſe to godly paſtours, who may and will giue them comfort out of the worde.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Let them confer with ſuch as haue
<pb facs="tcp:17063:32"/>
felt the like trouble, who will ſhew them how they got comforte therein: and that firſt of all, it is neceſſary for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to learne and vnderſtand fiue things 1. To knowe and confeſſe their ſins. 2. To feele them forgiuen in Chriſt. 3. To looke for pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of him to crucifie the ſame. 4. To lay hold vpon iuſtification by his reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. 5. To looke for ſtrength of him only to proceede to further ſanctification &amp; holines of life eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the end: al the which things they ſhall finde promiſed by God in his word, &amp; beleeued and put in prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe by the faithful, preached &amp; ſet down by the Prophets, as <hi>at what time ſoeuer a ſinner doth repent from the bottome of his heart, the Lord will put away all his iniquities, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And laſt of all, let them that bee thus troubled, ſay with the Prophete. <hi>Lorde, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is mercie with thee, that thou mayeſt be feared, I will wait vpon thee, as the eye of the ſeruant wayteth vpon the hand of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and I will condemne my ſelfe of folly, and ſay, ô my ſoule, why art thou ſo heauy? why art thou caſt downe within me? ſtill truſt in the Lord for he is thy health, &amp; thy ſaluation, &amp; therfore thou wilt truſt in him, albeit he ſhould ſlay thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They that ſute and ſeeke for theſe
<pb facs="tcp:17063:33"/>
means in the trouble of ther conſcience, with earneſt prayer, and feruent ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations vnto his holy maieſty in the name of his Chriſt, ſhall neuer but finde comforte to their wearied ſoules, and a full remedie to their wounded Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences in the ende.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Queſtion.</note>Laſt of all, (before I conclude) this queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may be moued. That if the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of conſcience be ſo feareful a thing, &amp; a quyet conſcience ſo excellent a trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure, why then is it that ſo manie are ſo carefull to preuent the troubles of the bodie, and ſo few carefull for the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of their ſoules and conſciences. For to provid remedies for povertie, &amp; Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick for ſicknes, we doe perceaue few to be ſlack or ſlouthfull, and yet to prouide any remedy in time for a ſick &amp; wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded Conſcience, we ſee few ſo carefull as will looſe an houres ſleepe. Example hereof wee may perceaue in <hi>Ioſephs</hi> brethren, who ſleeped with wounded and guiltie conſciences ſecurely, for the ſpace of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares, albeit they were very carefull ſo ſoone as they were puniſhed with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, to prouide a haſty remedy there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but regarded not the ſin commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:17063:33"/>
againſt <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> &amp; guiltines of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, vntill the Lord wakened them to their griefe. So did <hi>Dauid</hi> forget his murther and adulterie for a years ſpace, and ay &amp; while the Lord wakened him vp to repentance by his Prophet <hi>Nathan</hi> For anſwer to this queſtion, I ſay,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> that it is becauſe we deſire to colour our ſinnes and hyde the ſame, as did our firſt pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts vntill God himſelfe did reueale them, &amp; this chiefely doe all <hi>Adams</hi> children that are not renewed by Chriſt, and ſo ſhal all ſuch doe, as haue a ſleeping and careleſſe Conſcience (as haue moſte men at this day) vntill they be eyther wakend vp by gods Prophets, and his word to try their conſciences, or elſe by God himſelfe, by ſome inwarde griefe or outward trouble before their death, or in death to their endles griefe, or then after death to their euerlaſting damnation.</p>
               <p>Let vs therefore know, what thinge Conſcience is in time. What are the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of an euill Conſcience, what are the exerciſes or workes of Conſcience. What are the kinds &amp; ſortes of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences: and laſtly, what are mens dueties
<pb facs="tcp:17063:34"/>
concerning conſcience, and how he may get a good Conſcience, preſerue the ſame when it is gotten, and preuent the troubles thereof, and being troubled, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what maner he may be releiued out of the troubles of it. All the which things are expreſly to be found in Gods word: and therefore, let vs endeuour our ſelues ſeriouſly with earneſt prayer, to ſeeke them and ſearch them out of the ſame. That we may through patience &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte thereof, conceaue an aſſured hope (with the teſtimony of an excuſing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,<note place="margin">Rom, 15, 4</note> ſquared rightly with the rule of the word, of euerlaſting life, through Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord, To whome be all honour, prayſe and glory, for euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. John Howeſoun.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17063:34"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
